Welcome back to A-Push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. Hello there, to start this
video, I want to flashback to my final
Unit 5 video where I said this.
Reconstruction was the US's first
attempt at civil rights, and it failed
miserably. But, the 14th and 15th
Amendments didn't go away. They became
the legal foundation for the Civil
Rights Movement 100 years later. So,
yeah, it's finally 100 years later, and
it's time to talk about the Civil Rights
Movement. So, let's look at a typical
group of black Americans in the 1950s.
You might be surprised to know this, but
at this time, blacks were legally forced
to go to separate schools, use different
bathrooms and water fountains, sit in
the back of buses, and were often
blocked from voting, certain jobs, and
even neighborhoods, all because of the
color of their skin. So, now, a lot of
black soldiers fought for freedom in
World War II, and then they come back to
legally sanctioned segregation at home.
This was not sustainable anymore. So,
the big African-American rights
organization, the NAACP, went for a very
specific strategy to combat segregation.
And that strategy was challenging
segregation in courts, with a big lawyer
in this regard being Thurgood Marshall.
And this will all lead to our three
branches of government acting, albeit at
different times. In the executive
branch, Truman will desegregate the
military. In the judicial, the very
important Brown versus Board of
Education case happens, which declared
school segregation as unconstitutional,
meaning it overturned Plessy v.
Ferguson's separate but equal doctrine.
And finally, in the legislative branch,
the Civil Rights Act of 1957 was passed.
It was pretty weak and didn't really do
much, but it is symbolic as the first
civil rights law since Reconstruction.
So, now we see the Civil Rights Movement
expand. For example, courts became key
battlegrounds for arguing civil rights.
And obviously, we have our two main
civil rights organizations, and who can
forget the lady who refused to give up
her seat on a Montgomery bus. That's
right, Rosa Parks and Claudette Colvin.
Oh, and I guess Rosa Parks also did it,
too. After Rosa the got arrested for not
giving up her bus seat to a white man,
the black community in Montgomery
responded by boycotting the entire bus
system, causing it to lose a lot of
money with a key figure growing here
being Martin Luther King Jr. This would
lead to bus segregation being ruled
unconstitutional in Browder v. Gayle.
And finally, in a Little Rock, Arkansas,
nine black students enrolled at a
previously all-white high school. The
governor of Arkansas didn't like this
and tried to block these students from
entering school by sending in the
National Guard to block them, and
violent racism erupted as crowds
protested their entry. So, despite Brown
v. Board ruling segregation illegal,
Arkansas didn't care. So, President
Dwight D. Eisenhower had to act. So,
what he did was take control of the
National Guard away from the governor of
Arkansas, and even sent his own troops
to ensure the students could enter the
school safely. On the screen now are
AP-style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.